Vignesh Kannan





kvig.93@gmail.com | Fremont, California – 94538 | 813-405-9855 | https://www.linkedin.com/in/vignesh-kannan-98352877/

SUMMARY

SnowPro(Snowflake) Core Certified and AWS Certified Solutions Architect Associate Data Engineer with 7 years of experience in building data analytics solutions at scale and leading initiatives with expertise in data analytics, warehousing, architecture. Enthusiastic in solving complex data challenges and designing/building data systems from scratch.

EDUCATION

- Master of Science in Business Analytics and Information Systems University of South Florida, Tampa, USA. August 2019 - May 2021 with a GPA of 3.87.
- Bachelor of Technology in Information and Communication Technology SASTRA University, Thanjavur, India. July 2010 - May 2014 with a GPA of 7.14.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

- **Programming Languages**: Python, SQL, Javascript, R, HTML.
- Databases/Packages: MySQL, MS SQL Server, Postgres, Oracle, SSIS, SSMS.
- Python Frameworks/Libraries: Spark, Pandas, Numpy, PyTorch, Matplotlib, Kafka, Scikit-Learn, ML Libraries.
- Cloud/Data Warehouse/Big Data: Snowflake, Azure, Azure DevOps, Azure Data Factory (ADF), AWS EC2, AWS S3, AWS Glue, AWS Athena, Redshift, Hadoop, HDFS, Hive.
- Applications/Tools/Platforms: Snowflake, Databricks, DBT, Streamsets, Tableau, Power BI, JIRA, GitHub, Jenkins, Airflow, Terraform, Pycharm, Jupyter Notebook, MS Visual Studio, Docker, MS Word, Excel.

WORK EXPERIENCE

DATA ENGINEER – SOFTWARE AG USA INC., [SEP 2022 – November 2024]

- Designed, developed, and managed the administration of the Snowflake data warehouse as a part of the Analytics team.
- Architected the data solution end-to-end from scratch by developing databases, schemas, tables, roles in Snowflake and building cost efficient ELT pipelines using Streamsets, resource monitoring of consumption and costs, performed data modeling using **DBT** to create views which fed to **Tableau** and **Power BI**. Designed the data architecture for the analytics platform.
- Developed **Python** scripts for **extraction**, transformation and data quality checks. **Spark optimization** was done to reduce cost.
- Developed pipelines to extract from various Marketing Data (GTM) sources and Sales/Pre-Sales data from sources like Salesforce, Finance data from SAP and combining it with Product data to perform analytics and produce actionable insights.
- Implemented data validation, data governance and security guardrails in accordance with GDPR compliance and regulations.
- Led the team of data engineers, analytics engineers on various data initiatives. Mentored the team on Snowflake development.
- Reduced the cost of running self-serve analytics by \$4000 and increased efficiency of data processing by 30%.

DATA ENGINEER – TRELLANCE INC., [AUG 2021 – SEP 2022]

- Built a cloud solution in **Snowflake** data warehouse for **Credit Unions** in **Finance** domain as a part of an Application Development team. Designed and developed tables, schemas, roles in different layers using **SQL queries** in Snowflake.
- Developed **Python** scripts that processed data and migrated it to Snowflake. Developed **ETL pipelines** using **Pyspark** in **Azure Databricks** to process the data from source to Snowflake Datawarehouse.
- Worked on data migration from On-prem (MS SQL Server) hosted on an Azure VM to Snowflake by creating ETL processes and jobs. Worked in Agile environment with Scrum and CI/CD methodologies.
- Involved in reducing the cost by \$8000 per customer and time taken for the data processing by more than 50%.

SENIOR BATCH SPECIALIST – WIPRO LIMITED [MAY 2017 – MAY 2019]

- Developed **SQL queries** to create reports based on direct interaction with customers in the **Insurance** domain.
- Analyzed the code and optimized it to enhance the query execution by reducing the costs by 25%.
- Deployed code in the production environment with 100% success. **Involved in training and mentoring new recruits**.

SYSTEMS ENGINEER – TATA CONSULTANCY SERVICES [DECEMBER 2014 – DECEMBER 2016]

- Involved in migration of applications from **Mainframe** to **SAP** in **e-commerce** domain in a consulting/customer facing role.
- Worked through various steps of **Software Development Life Cycle** (SDLC) including gathering requirements from clients, requirement analysis and design, development, testing, implementation, maintenance. Experienced in Agile environment.